[
    {
      "question": "Q. What was the controversy between modernism and fundamentalism?",
      "answer": "A. The controversy arose between the “modernists,” who were liberals of the time (signers of the Auburn Affirmation), and fundamentalists (those who held that there were fundamental principles which must be believed by those to be ordained in the church."
    },
    {
      "question": "Q. What was the Auburn Affirmation?",
      "answer": "A. In 1923, a group of liberal-minded ministers in the northern church met at Auburn Theological Seminary (Auburn, NY). They adopted the position that the five fundamentals were theories, and therefore, did not have to be believed for a man to be ordained in the church."
    },
    {
      "question": "Q. What were the 'five fundamentals'?",
      "answer": "A. In 1910, the northern church (PC-USA) “adopted a statement of beliefs that came to be known as “the five fundamentals.” These five principles upheld the inerrancy of scripture, the Virgin Birth, the miracles of Christ, His substitutionary atonement for sin, and His bodily resurrection."
    },
    {
      "question": "Q. Who was Harry Emerson Fosdick?",
      "answer": "A. Fosdick was instrumental in attacking the fundamentalist movement, especially through a sermon, “What Should We Think of the Fundamentals?” He also was a significant party in drafting the Auburn Affirmation and instrumental in the unfrocking of Machen in 1939."
    },
    {
      "question": "Q. Who was J. Gresham Machen?",
      "answer": "A. Machen was the prominent leader in the battle against the Modernists. He wrote widely and spoke extensively for the cause of orthodoxy. Although much of the faculty of Princeton Theological Seminary supported him, there was still a division. The seminary in 1929 took steps to solve this division by joining the boards of trustees and directors. The new board had two signers of the Auburn Affirmation. This led Machen, Oswald T. Allis, Cornelius Van Til, and Dick Wilson to leave and form Westminster Theological Seminary in 1929."
    },
    {
      "question": "Q. Why did conservatives in the PC-USA form their own denomination, the Presbyterian Church of America, in 1936?",
      "answer": "A. Because of the modernist movement in the PC-USA."
    },
    {
      "question": "Q. What differences arose among the conservatives in the PCA after its formation?",
      "answer": "A. Differences along the lines of eschatology and the use or non-use of alcoholic beverages."
    },
    {
      "question": "Q. What was the result of these differences?",
      "answer": "A. The denomination split, with the group favoring pre-millennialism and complete abstinence from alcohol forming the Bible Presbyterian Church in 1938, and the PCA renaming itself to the Orthodox Presbyterian Church in 1939."
    },
    {
      "question": "Q. What happened to the BPC in 1956?",
      "answer": "A. The BPC split again, with one group under Carl McIntire resolving to keep mission boards and seminaries out from under denominational control, resulting in the BPC, Collingswood synod and the BPC, Columbus synod."
    },
    {
      "question": "Q. What happened to the Columbus synod?",
      "answer": "A. The Columbus synod changed its name to the Evangelical Presbyterian Church and soon merged with the Reformed Presbyterian Church of North America, general synod to form the Reformed Presbyterian Church Evangelical Synod (RPCES)."
    },
    {
      "question": "Q. Where did the RPCES come from?",
      "answer": "A. The RPCES came (albeit indirectly) out of the Presbyterian Church in the United States of America (Northern Presbyterian Church)."
    },
    {
      "question": "Q. What happened to the RPCES in 1982?",
      "answer": "A. The RPCES joined and was received by the PCA, bringing with them Covenant College in Lookout Mountain (Chattanooga, TN) and Covenant Theological Seminary in St. Louis, MO."
    },
    {
      "question": "Q. What was the significance of the Independent Board for Presbyterian Foreign Missions?",
      "answer": "A. The missions board was formed by Machen and others who formed Westminster Seminary, apart from control by the denomination, because the National Missions Board (PC-USA) was not permitting graduates to go to the mission field unless they submitted to their liberal theology."
    },
    {
      "question": "Q. Who was J. Oliver Buswell and what was his significance?",
      "answer": "A. Buswell contributed to the formation of the BPC out of the Presbyterian Church of America, was strongly pre-millennial, and stood for 'the separated life', meaning he believed any use of alcohol, cigarettes, etc. was wrong."
    },
    {
      "question": "Q. What was the issue that led to the formation of the BPC?",
      "answer": "A. The issue was the defeat of a resolution recommending abstinence from alcoholic beverages for the sake of a weaker brother, which led to the formation of the BPC."
    },
    {
      "question": "Q. Who was Robert Rayburn and what was his significance?",
      "answer": "A. Rayburn played a major role in the events that led to the split in the BPC, exposing dishonest practices in the American Council of Christian Churches, and was instrumental in the formation of a new college responsible to the synod."
    },
    {
      "question": "Q. Who was Francis Schaeffer and what was his significance?",
      "answer": "A. Schaeffer was instrumental in the joining and receiving of the RPCES with the PCA, and an advocate of 'the separate life' in the BPC."
    },
    {
      "question": "Q. Who was Carl McIntire and what was his significance?",
      "answer": "A. McIntire was a strong leader and pastor of the largest church when the BPC was formed, established the American Council of Christian Churches, and was strongly against having any committee or agency under the control of a denomination, but his isolationist views contributed to the breakup of the BPC."
    },
    {
      "question": "Q. When was the PCA first formed?",
      "answer": "A. The PCA was first formed in 1973."
    },
    {
      "question": "Q. Where did the first General Assembly of the PCA take place?",
      "answer": "A. The first General Assembly of the PCA took place in Birmingham, Alabama in December of 1973."
    },
    {
      "question": "Q. What were the four organizations that came together to form the PCA?",
      "answer": "A. The four organizations were The Presbyterian Journal, Presbyterian Evangelistic Fellowship (PEF), Concerned Presbyterians, and Presbyterians Churchmen United (PCU)."
    },
    {
      "question": "Q. What was the initial hope of the men in these organizations?",
      "answer": "A. Initially, they hoped that revival would take place in the Southern church and that the church would once again take a strong stand on principles, such as Biblical inerrancy and the obedience to ordination vows."
    },
    {
      "question": "Q. Why did the men of these organizations begin the process of building a new denomination?",
      "answer": "A. They began the process of building a new denomination because of the Southern church's chipping away at Biblical truth, which could no longer be tolerated."
    },
    {
      "question": "Q. What were some of the areas where the Southern church was chipping away at Biblical truth?",
      "answer": "A. Some of the areas included the development of a liberal educational curriculum, the ordination of men that did not hold a high view of Scripture, a decline in attitudes of the sanctity of life, and many other areas."
    },
    {
      "question": "Q. Who formed the PCA?",
      "answer": "A. The PCA was first formed by members of the Presbyterian Church in the United States (the Southern Presbyterian Church)."
    },
    {
      "question": "Q. What was the significance of the Presbyterian Evangelistic Fellowship (PEF)?",
      "answer": "A. The PEF was established in 1959 to pray for and promote Biblical Evangelism and spiritual revival in the PCUS and church universal, and brought an emphasis on evangelism and missions."
    },
    {
      "question": "Q. What was the significance of Concerned Presbyterians?",
      "answer": "A. Concerned Presbyterians was a laymen's organization that sought to inform the ruling elders and have them vote in their local sessions for the church to return to its Biblical roots, and called the whole church to prayer."
    },
    {
      "question": "Q. What was the significance of the Presbyterian Journal?",
      "answer": "A. The Presbyterian Journal was first formed in 1942 to attack liberal trends within the PCUS, and later worked to establish a new denomination when reform was deemed impossible."
    },
    {
      "question": "Q. Who was Morton H. Smith?",
      "answer": "A. Morton H. Smith was a member of the executive committee of the PCU."
    },
    {
      "question": "Q. Who was W. Jack Williamson?",
      "answer": "A. W. Jack Williamson was the secretary of the Concerned Presbyterians and the sole conservative voice on the Joint Committee of the PC-US that was to write the Plan of Union to unite the southern church (PC-US) with the more liberal northern Presbyterian church (PC-USA)."
    },
    {
      "question": "Q. Who was Ken Keyes?",
      "answer": "A. Ken Keyes was the first president of the Concerned Presbyterians."
    },
    {
      "question": "Q. Who was G. Aiken Taylor?",
      "answer": "A. G. Aiken Taylor was the editor of the Presbyterian Journal from 1959."
    },
    {
      "question": "Q. What is a distinctive of the PCA regarding General Assembly?",
      "answer": "A. In the PCA, all TEs are invited to GA, unlike the OPC which allots a number of seats by size of presbytery."
    },
    {
      "question": "Q. What is a distinctive of the PCA regarding eldership?",
      "answer": "A. The PCA holds to a two-office view of eldership, with less distinction between teaching and ruling elders, unlike the OPC which holds to a three-office view."
    }
]